Guide to the Stanford University, School of Engineering, Dean's Office, Records SC0165
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- General Correspondence, Series 1
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1937-1941 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Correspondence from and about Herbert Hoover and Herbert Hoover, Junior. From HH Senior about a statement issued by Stanford faculty about World War II; from HH Junior as American Geophysical Society experiments.
  - Hoover, Theodore, 1915-1944 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Professor of Mining Engineering from 1915 to 1925; Dean of the School of Engineering from 1925 to 1935. Miscellaneous correspondence and memoranda on all phases of Engineering School operation, various professional and administrative topics.
  - H - general correspondence, 1921-1933 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - H - general correspondence, 1934-1939 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - H - general correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - H - general correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - H - general correspondence, 1948-1955 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Independent Study Committee, 1927-1944 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    University-wide committee chaired by E.E. Robinson, and charged with developing and implementing programs of independent study for outstanding upper-division students. Minutes, memoranda, and reports.
  - Industrial Park, 1954-1963 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Correspondence and memoranda, primarily between Dean Terman, Alf Brandin, and corporate executives, about the desirability of locating plants in the Stanford Industrial Park.
  - I - general correspondence, 1925-1930 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - I - general correspondence, 1931-1942 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - I - general correspondence, 1952-1955 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - J - general correspondence, 1930-1942 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - J - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - K - general correspondence, 1928-1942 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - K - general conrespondence, 1946-1955 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Lesley, Everett P., 1945 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Professor emeritus of Engineering. Memorial resolution; obituary.
  - Libraries: Civil Engineering Library, 1935-1940 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Book and journal requisition requests submitted to Dean Morris by C.E. faculty; memoranda on budget and staff for Civil Engineering Library.
  - Libraries: Engineering, 1928-1939 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Report of committee of engineering faculty to study feasibility of establishing an engineering library; memoranda on gift funds and budget; applications for librarian position.
  - Libraries, Engineering, 1940-1945 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Correspondence about gifts to the library; requests for purchase of materials; annual reports by Engineering Librarian and Engineering School Library Committee.
  - Libraries: Engineering, 1946-1950 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Memoranda on book purchase fund expenditures; correspondence on gifts to library; annual reports of Librarian and Engineering School Library Committee.
  - Libraries: Hopkins Transportation Library, 1935-1944 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Memoranda on establishment, funding, staffing, and reference work in Hopkins Transportation Library.
  - Libraries: John Sontheimer Library Fund, 1955-1960 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Correspondence and memoranda about Urban Sontheimer's gifts to the University, including gift to Engineering School in honor of his son, John Sontheimer, M.E. 1942.
  - Liggett, J. B., 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Professor of Mechanical Engineering. "Report of Mr. J.B. Liggett, covering inspection of a number of plants in Milwaukee, Chicago, Detroit, Cleveland, etc., manufacturing different types of machiner." Typescript, 36 pp.
  - Lighting - general, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Memoranda between Dean Morris, President Tresidder, and Financial Vice-President Frank Walker about allocation of funds for, and adnrinistrative approval of, changes in engineering school light installations.
  - L - general correspondence, 1929-1938 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - L - general correspondence, 1939-1942 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - L - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - McGavin, Charles, 1926-1935 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    Engineering School alumnus. Correspondence betleen McGavin and Dean Hoover, after the former's graduation frorn Stanford, in which he reports on his post-graduation employment and interests.
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, 1920-1943 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Correspondence between book company and Dean's Office soliciting manuscripts; presenting complimentary copies of new engineering books; requesting miscellaneous information from office, etc.
  - Marx, Guido, 1925-1931 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    Memoranda betleen Marx and Dean Hoover on various subjects, including administrative heirarchy of engineering departments; proper recording of faculty meeting minutes; publications; committee appointments.
  - Marx Memorial Picture, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    Correspondence about solicitation to raise funds from engineering school alumni to purchase potrait of C. D. Marx for Engineering School. There was much controversy over manner in which solicitation was handled. Also correspondence about testimonial dinner for Marx in which portrait would be formally presented.
  - Mechanical Engineering Department, 1922-1928 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    Memoranda between Dean's Office and Mechanical Engineering Department; copies of M.E. department correspondence of interest to Dean. Various topics, including report on the state of, and future needs of, department; equipment purchase, use, and renovation; budget, curriculum, and faculty.
  - Mechanical Engineering Department, 1933-1943 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Mechanical Engineering Department, 1933-1943 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Mechanical Engineering Department, 1946-1956 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mechanical Engineering: Machine Design, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Correspondence and memoranda involving the Dean's Office and Mechanical Engineering Department related to Machine Design curriculum, personnel, and projects.
  - Mechanical Engineering: Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1926-1932 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Mechanical Engineering: Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1933-1943 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mining and Metallurgy Department.- Organization, 1911-1919 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Metallurgy was originally a branch of the Department of Geology and Mining. There was discontent with this system, because students interested in a career in mining engineering needed more emphasis on engineering, and less on geology, than the department offered. This folder deals with the plans to separate these two functions and create a mining and metallurgy department within Engineering. Includes correspondence and reports on various schemes for reorganization.
  - Mining and Metallurgy, 1920-1929 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Memoranda between Dean's Office and Mining and Metallurgy on miscellaneous business matters; copies of correspondencegenerated within the department of interest to the Dean.
  - Mining and Metallurgy, 1930-1935 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Mining and Metallurgy, 1936-1947 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Mining and Metallurgy: Appointments, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Mining and Metallurgy: Ceramics, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Report by W.F. Deitrich on proposed art ware pottery company that would use Stanford laboratories; Report of the activities of the Ceramics Division of the Department of Mining and Metallurgy.
  - Mining and Metallurgy: Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1925-1938 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Mining, Geology and Petroleum, 1936-1940 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    Memoranda, primarily between Dean Morris and President Wilbur, about possible establishment of a School of Mineral Sciences that would bring together in one school all geological and metallurgy classes that were then divided between the Schools of Engineering (Mining and Metallurgy) and Physical Sciences (Geology and Petroleum).
  - Mining, Geology, and Petroleum, 1936-1940 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Dean Morris was appointed by President Wilbur to chair a committee to investigate and report on the topic discussed in previous folder. This folder consists of committee minutes and reports.
  - Mining, Geology, and Petroleum Organization Committee, S.B. Morris' Personal File, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Morgan, Theodore H., 1930-1933 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Stanford Engineering alumnus; Assistant Professor of Electrical Engineering; later department head at Worcester Polytechnic Institute. Correspordence between Morgan ard Dean Hoover on summer activities; letter of recommendation; correspondence about publications.
  - Motion Picture Project, 1929-1930 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Dean Hoover, after a visit to Hollywood, became interested in develcpirg a curriculum in filmmaking. He wnote a report on his ideas (included in folder) and sent it to various members of the film industry for criticism, ard to attract potential contributions for the establishment of such a program. Folder consists primarily of correspondence with Hollywoodood film people following Hoover's visit ard report. Also includes text of speech by Professor Walter Miles about Muybridge's Stanford photographic experiments.
  - Municipal Engineering, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Correspondence and memoranda about proposed two year graduate curriculum in Civil Engineering leading to degree of Engineer in Municipal Engineering
  - M - general correspondence, 1926-1935 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - M - general correspondence, 1936-1939 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - M - general correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - M - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - McDonnell Correspondence, 1937-1945 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Mc - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - National Advisory Committee on Aeronautics, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Correspondence ard reports about Stanford. research in aeronautics in attempt to obtain funding support from NACA for Guggenheim Lab activities. Also correspondence about Charles Lindburgh's visit to Guggenheim Lab in 1939.
  - National Defense Research Committee, 1940-1955 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Correspondence with W.L. Everitt, head of Committee's communications section on military electronics problems; census of scientific personnel at Stanford involved in defense research.
  - National Emergency Committee, 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    Dean Morris was appointed by Dr. Wilbur to chair this committee. Concerns include emergency preparedness; draft; intensive courses in science and engineering to meet miliary requirements for scientific personnel.
  - National Emergency Committee: Research, 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    Responses to survey distributed by Dean Morris inquiring about equipment, personnel and defense research potential of all university departments.
  - Naval District, 1926-1936 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Correspondence between naval officials at district headquarters in San Francisco and various members of the Engineering faculty about laboratory facilities, testing equipment and engineering research at Stanford; sucessful campaign to establish Naval Air Station in Sunnyvale (Moffett Field); eligibility and recommendations for commission in Navy and Naval Reserve; Navy members studying at Stanford.
  - Naval District, 1937-1940 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Naval Flight Preparatory School, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Correspondence and information about possible Navy plan to take over Stanford as an "Annapolis of the West"; plans for pre-flight basic training for 600 cadets. Both plans were dropped by the Navy.
  - Naval Reserve, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Letters of recommendation for Stanford Engineering graduates seeking conmissions in Naval Reserve.
  - Navy: Post-Graduate Course, 1931-1932 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Correspondence and memoranda about arrangements between Stanford and U.S. Navy for naval personnel to take special post-graduate engineering training at Stanford.
  - Navy Research: Technical File, 1943-1948 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Correspondence, memoranda, graphs, technical drawings, and research notes related to Navy-sponsored research at Stanford.
  - Navy Research: Technical File, 1949-1951 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Network Calculator, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    Correspondence and memoranda about purchase and installation of an AC current network analyzer from Westinghouse Company, to be used in electrical engineering research.
  - N - general correspondence, 1923-1935 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - N - general correspondence, 1930-1942 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - N - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Ordnance, 1925-1927 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    The Engineering School was responsible for the Ordnance Division of R.O.T.C at Stanford. Ordnance used Engineering classrooms, laboratories, and some engineering faculty. Correspondence and memoranda relate to the arrangements nade between Stanford and the Army on all aspects of this relationship.
  - Ordnance, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Ordnance, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Ordnance, 1930-1931 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Ordnance, 1932-1934 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Ordnance, 1935-1937 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Ordnance, 1938-1940 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Ordnance Contracts, 1929-1932 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Ordnance: Explosives Laboratory, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Ordnance: Post-Graduate Training for Regular Officers, 1928-1933 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - O - general correspondence, 1927-1942 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - O - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Pacific Telephone, 1925-1934 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    Correspondence between Pacific Telephone Company and Dean Hoover about technical publications, engineering curriculum and research projects; employment opportunities for engineers.
  - Palmateer, Theron J., 1929-1930 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    Instructor in Machine Shop at Stanford. Articles by him on machine work; memoranda related to business of shop.
  - Pelton Water Wheel Company, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    Correspondence between Dean Hoover and Pelton Company on the history of the Pelton Water Wheel and its inventor, Lester Pelton.
  - Personnel Committee, 1926-1927 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    Correspondence and memoranda related to employment of Stanford engineering graduates.
  - Personnel Committee: Minutes, 1926-1927 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Personnel Committee: Subcommittee on Orientation, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Ph.D., 1928-1936 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Memoranda concerning school and departmental requirements for Ph.D.'s with major or minor in engineering.
  - Physics Department, 1926-1937 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    Memoranda between Physics and Engineering faculty, primarily D.L. Webster and Dean Hoover on curricula relevant to both departments; physics courses required by engineering students and vice-versa; teaching assignments.
  - President's Office Correspondence, 1925-1928 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    Memoranda between the President and Dean of Engineering.
  - President's Office Correspondence, 1929-1935 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - President's Office Correspondence, 1936-1940 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - President's Office Correspondence, 1941-1946 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - President: Astronomy, Geodesy, and Architecture, 1926-1928 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    Correspondence involving the President's Office about integrating studies ofastronomy, geodesy and architecture into Civil Engineering Department. Major field of interest is earthquake study, and proper architectural engineering to withstand earthquakes. Correspondents include Sidney Townley, Dean Hoover, Bailey Willis and R. L. Wilbur.
  - President: City Planning, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    "Preliminary suggestions for setting up at L.S.J.U a division or department of city planning. Prepared by Stephen Chi1d, Landscape architect." Report submitted to President Wilbur; comments by Dean Hoover.
  - Public Roads Administration, 1943-1944 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    Correspondence and memoranda about the possibility of establishing a highway laboratory at Stanford for the U.S. Public Roads Administration.
  - Publications Committee, 1925-1928, 1931-1936 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    Memoranda and sample copy written by the engineering school committee responsible for publication of engineering information in Coures and Degrees, Graduate Study Bulletin, etc.
  - Publications Committee, Agenda gnd Minutes, 1925-1931 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Publications: Committee on University Publications, 1928-1937 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    University-wide committee, of which Dean Hoover was a member, which approved manuscripts and budgets for Stanford's University Publications series
  - Purchasing Department, 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    Memoranda about wartime rationingof supplies and equipment; survey of important materials on hand.
  - P - general correspondence, 1926-1936 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - P - general correspondence, 1937-1942 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - P - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Quality Control by Statistical Methods, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    Correspondence and informational material on a special World War II course in quality control (particularly as applicable to war production industries) offered as part of the Engineering, Science and Management War Training Program, sponsored and financed by the U.S. Office of Education, and held at Stanford.
  - Q - general correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Rackwitz, Frederick, 1943-1947 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    Teaching assistant in Civil Engineering for the ASTP program; resigned when program was terminated. Memoranda about appointment, resignation; letters of recommendation.
  - Radar School, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    Correspondence and memoranda about possible establishment of an Army radar training school at Stanford. Correspondents include R. L. Wilbur, H.H. Skiiling, and F.E. Terman.
  - Radio, 1922-1929 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    Memoranda from Dean Hoover to R.L. Wilbur on the desirability of an educational radio station at Stanford, and its possible programming; responses fron various faculty members and alumni on the proposal.
  - Radio Talk, 1936-1937, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    Memoranda about scheduling and content of lecture given by Dean Morris on the Stanford University radio show on station KGO; text of Morris' talk.
  - Railroad Construction Indices, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    Correspondence about RCI subscriptions for the Engineering School; copies of some of the indices.
  - Railroad Engineering, 1928-1933 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    Memoranda about proposed engineering curriculum; employiment of college-educated men in railways.
  - Rankine Memorial Movement, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    Intercollegiate fund drive to establish a memorial to Wi11iam John McQuorn Rankine, an important Scottish physicist and engineer.
  - Refrigeration Engineering, 1924-1946 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    Correspondence about refrigeration curriculum in engineering school; letter from J.B. Howell, chief engineer of National Ice and Cold Storage Company on the history and future of refrigeration in the U.S.
  - Registrar, 1926-1938 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    Correspondence between the Dean's Office and Registrar on various topics, including degree requirements; student withdrawal from classes; curriculum; grading practices.
  - Registrar, 1939-1946 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Registration and Graduation, Committee on, 1926-1930 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    Minutes and supporting documents of this School of Engineering Committee.
  - Registration and Graduation, Committee on, 1931-1942 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Represa, California: Folsom Prison, 1938-1940 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    Correspondence between prison inmates and engineering school requesting technical information and discarded engineering equipment for prisoners' use.
  - Research - general, 1925-1945 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    Memoranda between engineering faculty and Dean about faculty research projects; progress reports; topics for future university research.
  - Research, Committee on, 1925-1941 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    Minutes and supporting documents related to research projects undertaken at Stanford.
  - Research, Petroleum, 1927-1928 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    Correspondence betrveen Dean Hoover and oil company executives about petroleum research projects at Stanford, and Stanford requests for financial support of such research.
  - Reserve Officers (Faculty), 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    Survey determining the military status of Stanford faculty members who were reserve officers; related information.
  - Reynolds, Ralph, 1938-1942 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    Correspondence between Reynolds and Morris about employment opportunities for Stanford engineering graduates; information and letters of recenmendation for applicants to Stanford.
  - Rice, Archie, 1933-1947 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Corespondence with Deans Hoover and
  - Riggs, Henry, 1937-1944 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    President of the American Society of Civil Engineers. Correspondence with Dean Morris about ASCE and other professional interests; and his visit to Stanford Engineering School.
  - Rocket Research, 1943-1944 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Memoranda about Stanford's desire to undertake U.S. Army rocket research. Includes correspondence from President Tresidder, Dean Morris, F.E. Terman, and D.L. Webster on status of American rocket research; possible research projects, and needs for future development.
  - Rock-Core - John Branner Newsome monument, 1939-1940 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    J.B. Newsome, Stanford alumnus (AB 1922, EM 1924) invented method of drillinh and removing solid cylindrical rock-core sections to excavate mine shafts at unprecedentedly low cost and high efficiency. This folder contains menos that relate to efforts to create monument to him at Stanford, using one of the rock cores excavated by his method.
  - Rose, Hugh, 1923-1931 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Personal friend of Dean Hoover. Correspondence with Hoover regarding Rose's son's application to Stanford.
  - Rosco Moss Company, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Correspondence between Rosco Moss, professional well contractor, and Dean Morris on hydraulics topics.
  - Rouse, Hunter, 1937-1938 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Candidate for teaching position in hydraulics at Stanford. Was unable to pursue candidacy for personal reasons. Correspondence with Dean Morris about qualifications, publications, and family situation.
  - R - general correspondence, 1927-1937 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - R - general correspondence, 1938-1942 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - R - general correspondence, 1943-1945 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - R - general correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Sadtler, Philip, 1939-1941 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Teaching assistant; applicant for graduate study fellowships. Correspondence with Dean Morris about terms of appointment and status of applications.
  - Safety Engineering, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    Memoranda betrveen J.B. Wells and H.H. Skilling on possible establishment of safety engineering study in connection with war emergencies.
  - Sah, A. Pen-Tung, 1944-1945 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    President of National University of Amoy in china. Visiting Professor of Electrical Engineering, spring quarter 1945. Correspondence about teacing position, travel arrangements; publicity material about his visit.
  - Salt Lake, City of, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    Correspondence betrveen H.K. Burton, superintendent of SLC waterworks, and Dean Morris about Stanford visit of Arthur Lezenky, engineer at the waterworks.
  - San Francisco Water Department, 1935-1940 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    Correspondence between Dean Morris and various engineers in SF water system about hydraulics and other professional interests.
  - Sanford, Homer, 1939-1940 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    Civil Engineer. Founder and Director of the Institute for Drilling Research. Correspondence with Dean Morris about the Institute, and Morris' possible affiliation with it